<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: technique | Steven You]]></title>
  <link href="http://GoSteven.com/blog/categories/technique/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://GoSteven.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-02T20:39:40+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://GoSteven.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven You]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vertically scale web application via using non-blocking I/O]]></title>
    <link href="http://GoSteven.com/blog/2012/07/28/vertically-scale-web-application-via-using-non-blocking-i-slash-o/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-28T21:51:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://GoSteven.com/blog/2012/07/28/vertically-scale-web-application-via-using-non-blocking-i-slash-o</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been working on web application scaling for a while. There are lots of interesting stuff. I will scale vertically first.</p>

<h2>Non-blocking I/O</h2>

<p>Blocking I/O means that the program execution is put on hold while the I/O is going on, which means the program waits until the I/O is finished and then continues it's execution.</p>

<p>However, in non-blocking I/O, the program can continue during I/O operations, and is notified via a callback when IO operation is finished. This forces programmers to design programs differently making them perform a lot better.</p>

<p>The Non-blocking I/O was supported by most Operation Systems. On Windows there is underlying OS support for non-blocking I/O, and Microsoft's CLR(Common Language Runtime, virtual machine component of .NET framework) takes advantage of that.</p>

<h2>Non-blocking I/O for web applications</h2>

<p>The implementation of non-blocking IO contribute the success of projects like <a href="http://nodejs.org/">node.js</a>.</p>

<p>For common web applications like JAVA Servlet, Apache web server , there is a design flaw, which introduce lots of overheads consume lots of mem and cpu because the thread is expensive. Non-blocking I/O is smart as the pending I/O connections will not consume any resources. On the other hand, underlying OS will be exhausted when looping through threads and checking status if each request will be handled via threads.</p>

<p>Here is a good slide describe node.js:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/2693037" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/marcusf/nonblocking-io-event-loops-and-nodejs" title="Non-blocking I/O, Event loops and node.js" target="_blank">Non-blocking I/O, Event loops and node.js</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/marcusf" target="_blank">Marcus Frödin</a></strong> </div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
